[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
[Music]
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se radio.net survey to
share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
your responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host akshay manchali my guest
today is luis size and we'll talk about
apache tvm
luis sazay is the ceo and co-founder of
octo ml a machine learning acceleration
platform designed to help developers
deploy machine learning models on
variety of hardware cloud and edge
devices octoamil was spun out of the
university of washington where luis is
also a professor there louise and a
number of his co-founders created apache
dvm a deep learning compiler which octo
ml is built on luis welcome to the show
really great to be here so before we dig
into tvm i want to cover some
fundamentals so just to set the context
can you start off by telling us what
apache tvm is apache tvm is a machine
learning deep learning model
optimization and compilation package
that takes models written in all of the
major frameworks for tensorflow pytorch
and mxnet carriers and so on it ingests
it to its internal representation and
there's a bunch of optimizations like
operator fusion data layouts it can do
quantization and so on and then it
produces a highly tuned binary for the
for a specific hardware target
essentially subsumes a lot of the manual
engineering required today to get your
model to be performant and to be ready
to be deployed in your platform of
choice and it supports a variety of
hardware targets including mobile cpu
service cpus mobile gpu server gpus
accelerators fpgas and so on let's talk
a little bit about the models itself so
in the entire life cycle of say machine
learning from when a data scientist
looks at a particular problem can you
describe how they go about building a
model and what does the model really
entail what does it contain or represent
absolutely and it's also great to make
it clear where apache tv fits in this
end-to-end from data to deployed model
right so so once upon a time you get
data right so data scientists work a
bunch of data they curate data sets to
train the models there's a lot of data
management and make sure you have you
know the right data to build your model
to test your model and so on and then
they find the general model
architectures that are for the problem
that they are interested in solving it
could be a computer vision focus
architecture could be natural language
processing could be time series
predictions there's a bunch of different
categories of architectures that data
scientists can consider and then they
use you know there's various tools to
help identify what is the best initial
model and you represent that model in a
framework like pi torch or tensorflow
which are declarative models that you
can declare what a model is supposed to
do
and then you run a training process the
training process takes this modern
architecture that you specified in the
framework and then ingested the training
data and really trains the parameters of
your model to make sure they perform
well on the training data and also
testing it against your test data set to
make sure the accuracy translates to to
data that was not included in the
training set okay so the result of all
of that is essentially
code that specifies what your model does
and a ton of data they're the parameters
that represent your model and as you
might have seen in the technical news
and the number of parameters and the
complexes the models keeps growing up
you know a lot you're talking about
models with tens of billions of
parameters it's not uncommon right
especially the language models have
they're very very large right so this
model as a collection of data and
code and a bunch of data needs to now
run on your deployment hardware right so
you might want to run it on a mobile
phone run it on a smart camera on a
self-driving car or you might run it in
the clouds as part of a cloud service
right so or a software service
application right so that process tends
to be pretty labor intensive because
typically models are effectively we call
interpreted right so there is a for each
part of your model there's a bit of code
that hardware vendors have written in
the form of libraries for example nvidia
has the kudn library that has bits of
code for each part of the model say
matrix multiplication convolution dot
products and so on
that if the execution engine stitches
them together as they're evaluating the
model and what apache2vm does instead of
actually interpreting the model it
produces fresh codes highly optimized
for the
end of hardware target right so you have
a model which is a bunch of code and
data and translates that into a binary
that runs in your target hardware so
let's talk about different kinds of
models a very simple machine learning
model that people get introduced to is a
linear or logistic regression model and
then the more sophisticated ones that
you're talking about say deep learning
that is involved in computer vision and
variety of emerging applications is a
more complicated model so can you tell
us what is the simple one what's
computationally involved and what's
computationally involved in the more
sophisticated ones it's a great question
and i would say that yes there's linear
regressions there's decision trees which
is like i would say classical machine
learning right so and then there is deep
learning and you know the more
sophisticated models for logistic
regression support vector machines and
deep learning
in the end it all boils down to a bunch
of linear algebra you're multiplying
matrices multiplying factors and so on
and what the difference between a simple
model and a complex in a complex model
is really just the amount of linear
algebra computation that you do i want
to be clear that even though my core
background is not in core machine
learning it's really about machine
learning systems right so i'll tell you
that it's a thing that people say often
is that if there's a simple machine
learning model that works well for what
you do that's what you should use right
you should only pay more complexity and
pay more computational costs and more
engineering if it actually brings you
value in the form of better predictive
power and better more accuracy for the
problems that you care about right the
big difference really fundamentally is
just how much computation you're doing
underneath right with deep learning you
have multiple layers and you have a lot
of what we call operators that are
stitched together that do convolutions
matrix multiplication you know
activation functions and in a in a very
complex data flow let's put it this way
whereas you know a simple logic
regression is just a very very simple
linear algebra computation right but
then there's another big one here that i
want to mention which decision threes
you know one example of a package that's
pretty common there's xg boost who
happened to have been started by our cto
as well tng chain
excuses is essentially the boosted trees
models essentially a collection of of
decision trees that can be evaluated can
be trained to find what are the decision
points from training data defines the
boundaries of the decision points in
your in your boosted three models and
extra boost is a package that evaluates
these models right so that's also part
of what people call classical machine
learning it's very important very widely
used and interestingly from a
computational point of view going deep
down getting closer to how your
processor sees it and how you execute
that at a first approximation be a bunch
of if then conditions right so you can
you can evaluate there's a bunch of if
then right so and that's one way of
doing it another way of doing it is also
doing it as linear algebra now it's
sparse linear algebra you can actually
convert this decision treats evaluations
as sparse linear algebra evaluation
expresses as a linear algebra expression
and once you do that it can actually
also run that through on a package like
tvm that just treats that
as if you were regular linear algebra
code and then still takes advantage
about the optimizations i know there's a
long answer to your question but i hope
it was useful you know so it was yeah
yeah it's a good overview interesting to
know about like xc boost and how it
works with decision trees so one aspect
of tvm i think is the portability of
your models where you can run it on
different target architectures but i
think there's another aspect which also
involves the performance and the
efficiency aspects of it if i have a
simple deep learning model that solves
some kind of a problem where does that
efficiency really come from from
specialized hardware or why specialized
hardware is actually useful for that let
me answer your question two parts first
let's let's ignore specialized hardware
first let's just talk about specialized
code where does the optimizations come
from and how do they bring performance
to a deep learning model on existing
typical say cpus and gpus right so where
tvm shines is really is doing
optimizations like okay once you have an
operator or you fuse two operators in
optimizing your model they are in the
end as i said a bunch of linear algebra
code that gets represented as loops over
data and performing operations like so
when you look at that there's many
things where you can change to get
performance for example you'd lay out
your multi-dimensional data structures
in memory in a way that you make better
use of your caches make values of memory
by just
organizing the memory in a more
convenient way for the hard work the
second thing is picking the right
instructions you know you know pick the
right vector instructions the right
scalar instructions you want to make
sure that you keep the data in registers
as much as possible there's a bunch of
scheduling decisions that you can make
other things are in what order can you
evaluate the loops right so for a given
deeply nasted loop you can change the
order of your loops have the same
computation but a given loop order is
much better than another one so if you
do the cross product of all these
decisions of data layouts loop ordering
how you tile the traversal of your data
structures and then the kind of
instructions you use you generate large
number of candidates per piece of code
right and picking the right one is on
the things that you know tvn does well
okay so great so and then what you get
in the end is really code that's highly
specialized to that model because that's
what seems to specialize to the data
layouts to the parameters of your code
you know you specialize the code great
so that's one thing now
how do we go further we go further by
making use of specialized hardware right
so and the trends today is pretty clear
as you can all see you keep hearing
about more and more ai chips or features
in popular hardware engines and you know
cpus gpus and new accelerators that are
dedicated to deep learning machine
learning in general that they actually
have hardwired circuits that perform an
operation a highly specialized way for
example a 2d convolution or an 8x8
matrix multiplication or a dot product
or an activation function like a sigmoid
function so you really hardwire that
into your circuits and when you do that
now i can put my computer architecture
ahead actually my core background is in
computer architecture right so the
efficiency there comes from the
following that in a general purpose
process or any general purpose circuit
you're going to have a lot of circuitry
that's making decisions of what you
should be doing at any given time like
should it be doing this or that right so
and that depends on the code well if you
build a hardwired circuit you don't have
to make those decisions you know exactly
what you're going to do you do only one
thing so you don't spend any circuits
you don't spend any energy or any time
figure out what you should be doing at
that given time right so that's where
fundamentally the specialization comes
from is that you remove this unnecessary
you know condition tests in the hardware
and then you can optimize your circuit
you're going to have shorter wires
you're going to have less memory and you
know if you have shorter wires it's
faster right so you can more transistor
dedicated to actually use for
computation that's from a harder point
of view but then that specialized unit
in your hardware needs to be invoked by
your software somehow so whenever you
have a specialized unit there will be a
specialized instruction that typically
looks very strange you know like this
really complicated instruction that you
have to invoke somehow and making use of
that you can either be you know a super
low level programmer that's going to go
and use that assembly instruction right
there and know exactly how to use it
those are rare and we don't have to rely
on those too much right and for too long
unfortunately a lot of low-level
libraries rely on low-level assembly
code tuning which is something that
that's where you don't want to be but
the way this works in tvm and other
machine learning compilers is that there
are ways of actually matching what
you're trying to do in your model with a
primitive available in the hardware this
problem sounds easy but it's actually
fairly complex because the more complex
the operation behind it the more
difficult is the pattern matching to
make sure that you're using the right
instruction right so
does that give you an overview does that
sound good yeah yeah yeah i guess
something to understand here is the
complexity also involved in actually
writing that sort of specialized
instruction for assembly right so how
complicated is that for something that's
very simple as a linear regression model
which is something that might be more
sophisticated with multiple you know
composed of many many operators
let's drill down in one right so let's
say if you're just doing a simple eight
by eight matrix multiplication hardware
that you want to invoke let's keep it
super simple okay so what do you need to
do well that instruction that you invoke
with a single primitive hardware takes a
bunch of inputs you have to know how the
hardware expects to see the data in
memory and where it expects it to be
when you say go okay so when you
actually invoke the instruction and then
the output is put in another buffer that
you have to go get it from there and put
it where you need to go for it to give
the input to the next layer so all of
these things you need to understand what
is the data format where should they be
you know where is the output and then
also how long does that take to execute
because remember that it's all about
parallelism here and then whenever
you're invoking this instruction there's
some other stuff going on so you want to
know that you're scheduling this right
right so you know when i kick this off
you have another and i know it's going
to take so long for the results to be
ready i think a bunch of the stuff in
between right so does that give you an
idea of how complex it because this can
get you just matching the inputs and
outputs but also understanding things of
what are the performance implications of
using that instruction and what else
could be done in parallel right so you
would do this with a single target
architecture in mind and i suppose you'd
have to do this all over again if you
were to change your implementation
change your target architecture you're
redoing all of this is that right bingo
that's exactly right so that's one of
the reasons why
there is major let's say vendor lock-in
and major reluctance in changing you
know what architecture gonna deploy your
your model to because making the most
out of a harder target for something as
performance sensitive as this kind of
code involved in machine learning it's
very very labor intensive so you
definitely want to stick with an
architecture for as long as possible and
last you have an automated way of tuning
your code to different different
architectures so you can move more
easily right and performance portability
is one of the things that we really
believe in and in fact if if i may we
care about three p's here in machine
learning we care about performance
portability and productivity right you
want to make the most out of the
hardware data deploy to it'll be able to
port it right so portability to change
its different hardware you want to be
productive and you want to rely as
little as possible on this hard
engineering labor having to tune the low
level aspects of your code
our sponsor for this episode is spot by
netapp spot provides a comprehensive
suite of cloud ops tools that make it
easy to deliver continuously optimized
and reliable infrastructure at the
lowest possible cost imagine automating
your infrastructure to proactively meet
the needs of your applications imagine
leveraging the latest in machine
learning and automation to scale your
infrastructure using the most efficient
mix of instances and pricing models
eliminating the risks of
over-provisioning and expensive lock-in
from cost management to infrastructure
automation and cd to running serverless
spark on kubernetes spot ensures you
maximize your cloud investment the end
result is simply more cloud at less cost
discover how the most innovative
companies from cloud native growth
machines to forward-thinking enterprises
are automating simplifying and
optimizing their cloud infrastructures
with spot by netapp
check them out at spot.io
se radio where you can find more
information request the demo or give a
try by starting a free trial
let's dig into
tvm itself tvm in some sense is a
compiler that takes in a model and then
gives you target architecture code
traditionally compilers have this whole
concept of having the front end and a
back end where the front end parses and
then the back end does the optimization
and code generation
so can you talk about what tvm does in
that context like as a classical
compiler let's say that you have a model
in in tensorflow you can also have a
model in a generic form called onyx that
has been around for some time and now
it's keeps getting better and better so
you represent your model in a high-level
framework or in something like onyx and
then tvm ingests it into its first level
intermediate presentation called relay
relay is a typed data flow graph okay so
it's an ion intermediate presentation
that represents your model as a graph
where each node is an operator say a
matrix multiplication or convolution or
an activation function and so on and
then the edges and the data transfers
are typed so you know what is the shape
of your tensor what are the dimensions
and the data type right the dimensions
of your tensor the ranks and also the
data type what is a tensor can you
describe that oh yeah absolutely thank
you
sometimes you take this for granted
thank you for bringing it up yeah a
tensor is a multi-dimensional data
structure think of it as a
generalization of a matrix right so you
could have three dimensions right so the
matrix is two dimensions and then a
tensor could have a an arbitrary number
of dimensions very useful machine
learning because then it can represent
many things in each dimensions right so
tends to think of it as a general
abstraction of a linear algebra data
item okay okay yeah great
so then relay is this data flow graph
that's typed and at that level tdm can
do a bunch of optimizations right they
can decide to fuse two operators so
let's say that you have a convolution
followed by a matrix multiplication and
then you can fuse that into a single
more complex operator that can do both
of those together okay so those
decisions can be done at that level you
can also make decisions like okay so for
this group of operators it's better if i
run in a cpu for this group of operators
it's better if i run in a gpu or for the
other group of operators it's better if
you're running a specialized accelerator
it's a great place for you to do what we
call device placement where these models
can get pretty complex and different
execution and using hardware are better
for different things so you can
partition where those run all right so
tvm represents the model that level does
is high level optimizations can do
things like quantization as well by that
i really mean changing the data type say
if you have a 32-bit floating point
number you might be able to just say you
know what this might be okay if i did an
int8 go integer with eight bits you lose
dynamic range but you can still
represent what you need with fairly good
accuracy and then you just reduce the
conditional cost dramatically when you
do that right so not only go from
floating points to fixed points but you
also reduce the number of bits per data
item and then what you do is you
actually keep lowering this this was a
data flow graph level as you lower it
down you're going to lower it to another
intermediate representation called the
tensor intermediate representation so
that's pure linear algebra expressions
okay so you're going to learn from data
flow to these linear algebra expressions
and that's where you can actually get
bits and pieces of this expression and
start figuring out how do you better map
that
to the available primitives in the
target hardware so at that level cvm can
do a bunch of more hardware specific
optimizations that's when you do data
layout optimizations when you make
selections of what kind of instructions
you're going to use that's where you
make selection what order you do the
loops and so on and that's actually done
by a process called auto tuning which
maybe we can talk about later but
basically auto-tuning is about
generating a large number of candidates
and picking what's the best one in that
specific hardware by doing a bunch of
empirical experiments and then once you
do that you keep lowering we say
lowering we lower from the model to data
flow graph level to the data flow graph
to tensor expressions to this expression
to low-level machine code or sometimes a
low-level intermediate representation
like for example allow vm or a lower
level ir
and what happens with target hardware
architectures that don't necessarily
expose an instruction but give you a
library is the lowest thing translating
into the library that's an excellent
question yeah so we use the lowest level
api available for your hardware target
right so for example nvidia gpus they do
not expose the raw instruction sets
right so we don't know what it is but we
can generate cuda code which is
essentially the low level api right so
the level programming interface for that
hardware targets it's not quite the
library level it's really expressing the
actual tasks that you want to do on the
hardware anyways and this is i think
it's a good moment to mention that the
reason that tvm can do what it does for
machine learning it's because it's
optimization passes and the intermediate
representation preserves enough semantic
information what is that you're trying
to do i don't want to get you know
annoying and remind you maybe of your
compiler classes here but it's all about
how much information is available for
your optimization pass the more you know
about what the programmer actually
wanted to do the better translations you
can do and the great thing about
specializing in a compiler stack to
machine learning is that you preserve
this intention the intent of the
programmer had and that enables
optimization that wouldn't be possible
if you had to rediscover that from the
low level
put another way for example i can't just
write a machine learning code and say c
that's effectively doing machine
learning in a binary and then use that
into tvm because you don't really have
that semantic information exactly right
if i give you a bunch of assembly code
it'd be very hard for you to discover
that
looks like you're doing a matrix
multiplication oh it looks like you're
doing a logistic regression right so
that's hard right so and preserving that
at a high level enables pretty
significant optimizations so what sort
of libraries or model descriptions do
you support can you describe that
landscape of what's available like i
know pytorch is one onyx is one so what
do these things describe the models as
and how do you consume them i think it's
fair to say there are declarative ways
of describing your model you declare
what the layers look like you say i have
a convolutional layer you know i have an
activation function i have a matrix
application i have you know you describe
what the layers look like and where the
inputs go to the outputs effectively
describing this data flow graph that
relay reconstructs in an abstract way
right it's exactly what all of them does
in fact tensorflow the name really means
tensorflow you float tensors between
operators it's a fairly general concept
of declaring a data flow graph and
expressing very clearly what is the data
type
let's talk about the optimizations that
you mentioned that tbm can actually
perform on your input model so one thing
is you said operator optimizations where
you confuse so do you have a simple
example maybe that people not deep into
machine learning can possibly follow or
understand what sort of optimizations
are actually possible the highest level
one is is really what we call hyper
parameter tuning right essentially you
have parameters in your model hyper
parameters of describes aspects of your
architecture you can tune and optimize
for the use case for the target
deployment so these are outside tdm's
domain because the way we think about is
that the model that tvm takes as input
is essentially a model has had its
parameter tuned it's paramount like it's
hyper parameters soon and even a
parameter is all trained for that's not
part of our demand that means really we
treat tvm tweets uh a model as a program
to be compiled to specific harder target
it doesn't change the model except for
quantization where you change the data
type by and large cvm does not change
your model and the type of transitions
that it does is what i described before
right it really finds the way the best
way of how to lay out the data
structures in memory for each one of
your tensors right so it figures out
what are the right instructions to use
in the in the harder target it figures
out in what order you want to execute
the loops and all of that leads to a
large space of possibilities that tvm
navigates and produces the right the
right code did answer your question
actually i said what are you asking her
yeah in a way yeah regarding the kind of
instructions that you can use i think
people who are writing normal systems
programs for channel group or cpu they
might be familiar with x86 cmd
instructions which operates on a vector
of data so are there more specialized
ones coming out of specialized hardware
that you can exploit absolutely so some
of them are activation functions that
are hardwired right so if you have a
sigmoid function that you trying to
represent in software you can just call
it in a specialized hardware might have
one that does that in a single like in
one go right the other one is
convolution two deconvolutions some
popular convolutions that you tend to
express as codes with multiple hardware
primitives in a typical processor with a
series of sim the instructions you can
write you can execute as a single
operator in hardware that's another one
and then you keep specializing right so
basically the game here that these ai
chip companies are playing is
essentially looking at the model
architecture looking what are the
popular models want to do and then
hardwiring as much of that as possible
as a single big blob that you can call
and this is why it's becoming quite of a
zoo out there right so because the
number of species a number of different
primitives available in all the heart
attacks it's so it's overwhelmingly
large and navigating that is hard that's
one of the big motivations why we built
tvm too is dealing with this camera and
explosion of hardware targets and
hardware options and offer a clean
abstraction so is that where the auto
tuning and searching through that space
of possible instructions that you can
benefit from for your model is that
where it comes from in part yeah so the
autotune is general it's even for just
cpus suppose that you have a convolution
right so that you have code for and now
as i said there's going to be nested
loops this is going to call some
existing hardware primitives the vector
primitives that might be available and
it takes as input some specific data
types they write some specific tensors
so now when you do the cross product
between data layouts loop ordering
tiling and then hardware instruction
choices it's easy to get to you know
hundreds of millions not billions of
possibilities right so for the same
piece of code all of them are
semantically valid all of them are
likely to do or they should do exactly
the same thing but for bits the question
is how do you pick the fastest one there
might be one that's 100 times faster
than the other one right so one brute
force way of doing that is trying them
all
but now you might be thinking already
see you here like everything well this
this is going to take a while right so
imagine this you're generating a code
variant
you are compiling it down you're running
it you're measuring it and making a
decision whether or not that's faster
than your previous version right so and
then you can pick the fastest one right
so if it's in the other billions and it
takes a second to do that that's a lot
of time it's a lot of computational
costs a billion seconds is a long time
right so what we're doing tvm and this
is now others are doing this too and
some of the general technique has been
popular in high performance computing
for some time is to essentially create a
very fast
and fairly accurate way of predicting
whether a given alternative in autotune
is actually likely to be good or better
than you had before right so given a set
of alternatives can you rank them
without having to compile run and
measure so the way we do that is by
building a machine learning model that
predicts performance properties of
pieces of code so given this template
that i told you about and you have this
set of parameters you would fill in to
go and compile run and measure
we extract that as features we run a few
times and we build a predictive model
that says that based on these features
of and decision making the code you know
how can you predict whether or not
something's faster right so you could
try and predict the actual runtime but
that's hard then you can do that people
have done that some extent but i think
it's much more interesting to say given
a set of alternatives tell me which one
is likely to be the fastest one without
running any of them just based on their
features and that's what we do like we
do this it's somewhat dependent on the
specific code template and the hardware
target and we had a paper about this in
eurips and it's a good chunk of tng
chance phd thesis he's a pharmaceutical
co-advised his co-founder and cto over
company and also professor at carnegie
mellon university now to really
brilliant work that showed that you can
actually create these predictors fairly
accurately and use that to speed up to
20. so how do you use that well these
models evaluate instead of seconds they
can take milliseconds or less in some
cases they can actually push it down to
microseconds so that means they make
something a million times faster so now
you can actually get for all these large
returns you can pick which one should
you actually run now instead of actually
running a billion you can run just a
handful 100 maybe you know 50 or 100 and
then you pick the fastest one all right
so and this is fairly accurate and
that's how we do it so we use that to
predict what's the fastest version and
in case you're interested you know it's
the super interesting question of
building these library predictors for
pieces of code to specific heart attack
it starts to translate to other hardware
architectures that are similar enough
another piece of code is similar so
there's transfer learning opportunities
there too
i think i'm missing one aspect so let's
say i
i use tvm i download the library and i
feed my model in and i have my target
architecture which might be a gpu or
something and i want to benefit from
this auto tuning capability but i've
never used this before but also you have
a model that kind of predicts which
might be good right so the way i
understand it sometimes you you need
some training data in order to kind of
like say oh yeah this is actually faster
or this decision is correct so how do
you bootstrap that in just right out of
the box
when you install tvm and you want to run
it and you use auto tuning you have to
have a hardware harness like you have to
have a benchmarking test bed right so
and that could be one gpu or one zip or
whatever you're doing like you have a
few of them to parallelize that and it
runs a little experiments to bootstrap
that so it actually starts by running a
few experiments and extracts the
training data it trains it and then it
keeps improving the model along the way
as a quick plug here if i if i make so
if you use say optimal sas platform we
have that training data just ready to go
typically we have the models ready to go
and also we have the hardware testbed
ready for you to use both for you know
cpus gpus are available in the cloud but
also you know edge cpus and gpus as well
but otherwise you need the target
architecture to be able to kind of like
let it get better yeah and you have to
set it up and you have to measure like
you know part of the
value add here of using the sas platform
is that you don't have to do any of is
turnkey right you can even invoke the
service with two lines of code by our
api so
se radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se radio.net survey to
share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
your responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
with all of this sort of optimizations
one thing you mentioned earlier was
quantization where you might convert say
floating point ones into integers
because they might fit better so does
that change the
end result the accuracy of model yes it
does so the question here is that how do
you do that in a way that change it as
little as possible right so there are
many ways of dealing with that like one
way is to quantize and then retrain it a
bit like refine the training a little
bit so you can refine the parameters
this has a cost you know it's not ideal
other things you could do and we had a
paper
that josh from our head of machine
learning systems at at octomow and also
uw phd he wrote a paper that mouse says
they was published last year and was
2020 that talked about ways of actually
estimating accuracy in a local way right
so essentially you can make decisions
just by evaluating portions of your
model not end to end you can make good
decisions about how much you can
quantize without affecting the accuracy
we have versions of that and we can
evaluate and bound the level of accuracy
degradation without having to retrain it
i don't want to go too deep on the paper
we can talk more about that it could be
a whole other conversation but basically
you can make very local estimations of
accuracy degradation with a synthetic
input you don't have real data so we
don't want to be exposed to real data
because that's complicated right so we
can actually estimate accuracy
degradation with synthetic data right
there for parts of your model but then
what we want to offer the user in the
end is that for their data we're going
to give them a pareto curve that says
performance gain and accuracy
degradation so you can pick what your
level of tolerance is right so some
people might say okay i want to take a
you know 0.1 accuracy degradation if i
get at least 2x performance gain for
example you can make those decisions
based on a curve of accuracy degradation
versus performance gain is that
something that you can tune into tvm as
an input or is that just an experimental
kind of a thing where you try it out and
see where it falls on that curve you can
actually build an outer loop onto them
today and some people have done that in
fact we've had papers that showed that
you showed that that's how riptide that
this paper they talked about did it and
i know that others have built you know
this outer loop into vm to make those
decisions too so that's very interesting
in terms of
actually deploying to the hardware
target architecture you know that's kind
of like towards the end of the machine
learning life cycle to so to speak right
are practitioners you know data
scientists somehow aware of where
they're going to deploy it in the end is
that going to change their decision
making about whether they use a certain
type of parameter or not we want data
scientists to not have to worry about
that the unfortunate reality today is
that data scientists and folks beauty
machine remodels tend to worry about the
cost of their models
and how they're going to deploy them too
early like if they know they're going to
deploy on a gpu because that's what they
have available that's what cost
effective they start affecting their
model design decisions too early and i
think that hurts them because they might
be making decisions that would you know
not make them go in the direction that
the model be better more accurate and if
they had gone that way at the end they
would have an accurate model and then
let's things like tvm or tensority or
other other optimizers and they'll do
their job and recoup a lot of
performance later so our vision here is
to free data scientists from having to
worry about these deployment aspects
early on in the modern development we
want them to develop the models with
their primary goal in mind which is
build the best model that they can with
the data that they have in mind because
today the reality is that they do the
best model with the data they have in
mind
and some deployment constraints we want
to say like remove deployment
constraints build your best model and
abstract the deployment aspect away and
leave that to folks like us that are
that do that for a living right so yeah
no that makes a lot of sense because you
know if you're a data scientist you
might not have a computer science
background a deep systems background to
be able to make those decisions early on
so it makes sense for them to not worry
about that that's very useful i think
yeah you know that just reminds me of
this this quote early optimization is
the root of all evil in programming have
you heard that before yeah like you know
if you premature optimizations are bad
because you increase code complexity and
make harder to maintain and it's not
clear if it pays off because if you do
that you might preclude other
optimizations later we say that in
writing regular code and i feel like
we're talking about here is a similar
thing here in machine learning where you
know trying to optimize for deployment
and the process of developing your model
early on it's just premature
optimization that should not be part of
the story right
there's a lot of like magic happening
underneath if i'm a data scientist that
i'm saying okay this is the model and i
hand this over to run it in some target
architecture there's a lot of what
appears to be just magic before it runs
on the target architecture how do they
go about say debugging understanding you
know whether the model is performing
that the way they actually expected it
model observability and debugging is a
big topic in what is now being called
mlaps you know parallel to devops but
for machine learning models let's start
with debugging right so part of the
debugging you know be done and model
development just makes you like your
model is misbehaving with some specific
class of inputs a lot of that should be
done you know if the model was done
right you should have actually had a
pretty good representative data sets to
test
but sometimes you're just not exposed to
that so what you need to do is just add
instrumentation to your model and then
if there are surprises in deployment you
collect those inputs and then you feed
this back and then go and refine your
model okay so that's one way of doing
that you put some safeguards to know hey
your model is is misbehaving because you
have ways of doing some control tests
and then whenever it fails or there's
some inputs where you know some guard
rails are tripped you know you collect
the data and then you go back to model
refinement that's one way of doing it
otherwise it's just like doing we call
model explainability which is
essentially trying to describe
what is it that a machine learning model
is doing to a to a human being that is a
domain expert and then if you eyeball
that you can see like okay you know what
let's let me give you an example that's
a classic one if you're gonna make a
machine learning model for medical
diagnostics right so typically this is a
black box and it can be very accurate
against that sets but then it could lead
to surprises that can be very costly
when you're making decisions that affect
directly affect human lives in terms of
health care decisions right so what you
want there is to be able to abstract
that model in a way that you can expose
to a panel of medical experts that can
look at the most like oh this decision
here doesn't seem right right so this
model explainability is also a hot topic
in aiml research and is turning into
practice today with several emerging
companies like y labs for example works
on mod observability and model
explainability that makes you understand
you know not only what your mod is doing
but also you know how is it performing
in deployment by looking for anomalies
and so on you would have to do that
early on rather than in the end but you
can observe what it's like at the end i
guess you do that along the way right so
say that once you have a model ready to
be deployed what you want to do is add
instrumentation to monitor how the model
is doing and collect inputs when some
unexacted conditions are matched that's
one way and the other one is just try to
explain the model explainability so
before you deploy to explain the model
you just make sure that is it are there
any
potential bad scenarios here that aren't
being covered or scenarios that are
unlikely but aren't being covered well
by the model so that you do that with
model explainability tvm and one in a
way you know you can run this on
multiple target architectures and what
are the reasons one is like we've
discussed about performance in order to
get the best out of your model but are
there other reasons why you would want
to run it on different target
architectures are there other
motivations to use this
there's many one is you might have no
choice right so let me give an example
you installed a bunch of cameras that
have local computing them and you want
to do computer vision in them you know
cameras could be installed like you have
a large installed base you don't have a
choice you have to live with whatever
architecture is there your model has to
run there so that's one this is likely
to be true for for self-driving cars and
then autonomous vehicles in general
whereas you deploy a fleet of those it's
actually it takes work where you're
going to upgrade the car you have no
choice if you're on your if you want a
better model to run and make your
self-driving car safer and better and so
on you got to live with the architecture
that has been deployed that's one right
so and in that case and also mobile
phones right you're going to be able to
cover as many mobile phones as possible
say if you are deploying a model to
android phones there's a large number of
chips that are different across android
phones and you have to live with the
collection of the users that you have
right so and in that case when you want
to live with the diversity in a second
you want to make sure that your model is
fast enough and uses has resource
requirements are compatible with how
you're going to deploy it and that's
doing optimizations like what tvm does
is an enabler right so in some use cases
we've had here it was deployed in a
pretty unique but popular architecture
that is deployed in cameras and we offer
a 30x better performance and there was a
difference between actually being able
to deploy versus not being able to
deploy right so that's one the second
one
is when you're deploying models in the
cloud you have throughput per dollar
constraint right if you're running a
model at scale and you're doing say tens
of millions or maybe hundreds of
millions of inferences a day it adds up
pretty quickly and that can be very very
significant cloud bill and what's great
about that you know use case is that if
you make your model 2x faster
fundamentally make it to x cheaper
because you used to ask your cloud
resources right so
and in that case what you want to do is
be able to
pick for a given model and a wealth of
instances that you can choose from you
want to pick the one that gives you the
highest food per dollar but today if you
have to do manual engineering for each
one of those first of all you delay time
to market too much right so because now
you have to tune against all these
architectures and then second sometimes
it's not cost effective because you're
going to pay engineering time to do that
and it might not be a win in the end
because now what you're going to say
with the vibrational cost is not worth
it right so being able to move around
and deploy into the most cost-effective
cloud architecture is another another
use case and the third one is even for
cloud-based appointments sometimes
latency is a big factor right so let me
give an example if you're using document
analysis or if you're doing and you want
to play the document you're going to
know immediately whether or not you know
there's something you should look at in
your model there's human interactivity
right chatbots another one you wanna you
wanna be able to evaluate your language
model fast enough right so that means
that if you have a model that does has
better accuracy and leads to a better
product experience but it's too slow to
run on the available hardware today
you can ship it right so an enabler is
when you hit the certain performance
target and then cost savings is because
you save costs in the cloud or even save
costs in the edge so if you're building
a purpose-built device to monitor
something in the field using machine
learning you want to find the cheapest
hardware that can do that right so
instead of overshooting yeah that makes
a lot of sense i mean like you said it's
an enabler and which is why you know as
consumers we see
machine learning being used in a variety
of different ways in our daily basis
when we interact with computers and or
even outside of it so voice assistants
and things like that so that's very cool
i wanted to switch gears a little bit
and talk about the engineering behind
tvm itself traditionally compilers are
difficult if you're studying it in
school it's probably the hardest thing
that you can study if you're actually
working on it it's probably the hardest
thing that you can work on because
there's a certain expectation of like
accuracy and correctness that isn't
normally expected of other software i'm
sure most people will go their entire
software engineering careers without
encountering a compiler bug so
you're building something that is
slightly different where you have some
amount of like fuzziness in what your
programs itself are doing so how do you
go about engineering building it and
testing for correctness first of all
engineering i can't pass up the
opportunity to say that you know tvm is
now has a big develop open source
developer community we have more than
570 lifetime contributors to tvm so it's
it's really a huge effort that we're
extremely grateful to and we and i think
that compilers given the the complexity
of what it does
but also the diversity of models
frameworks and harder target the cross
product is wide so the only way we can
make the future proof and make that even
tractable is by having folks
contributing from multiple angles you
know machine learning engineers to
support new models harder than
supporting harder targets and folks in
the middle like to improve and enrich
the infrastructure right so that's just
to say there's a lot of you know really
talented developers have have
contributed code to it so and then how
do we do with correctness well one of
the great things about compiler is that
despite being complex right is that you
have very well defined rules on how you
do transformations in your code right so
you can take a formal verification
approach you know then folks have talked
about formally verifying parts of what
tvm does and that might have happened
and i apologize i know exactly what part
of it might have had that but biology
just do like very very thorough testing
right so we have cascades that has you
know the validity of transformations and
in isolation and then ways of showing
that they can compose and and so on
right so we could go and do more and
more formal verification but as you know
pharma verification does not scale
very well so you have to do it in a very
very limited way so so just i would say
that i do so like a boring answer but it
boils down to the very very thorough
testing and have really good task
coverage for correctness and performance
regression right
since you have a variety of hardware
targets are there hardware designers who
actually write code for tvm in terms of
like actual code generation one of our
co-founders and my former phd student
terry monroe in fact part of his thesis
was a open source deep learning
accelerator the design is open by the
way and it's also part of the cvm
overall package called vt versatile
tensor accelerator and that's one
example of hydrosofter co-design design
the architecture with an isa that gets
exposed to vm and in that case terry
who's the main hardware designer there
there's a lot others involved but he was
the lead designer they got involved in
essentially finding ways of exposing the
isa such that tvm can do its
optimizations right so that's one
example that happened historically but
to answer your question more directly
yes so we do have harder vendors that
contribute code directly and they tend
to understand the architecture really
well and that can help of course you
know in being able to have the right
hooks to enable different types of
optimizations in in tdm for example it's
no secret that you know arm is a big
participant in the tvm community amd is
a big participant qualcomm is a big
participant in the tvm community and
we're starting to see other hard events
contributed to like xilinx for example
and so on and we see some you know folks
on nvidia tender conferences as well and
we saw a little bit of commits from them
some examples of of course all the
vendors are sensitive to not embedding
sensitive ip but what they're doing is
not doing anything as hardwired to that
hardware there so essentially writing
the right primitives to be able to doing
auto tuning and doing the code
transformations be able to support the
primitives well let's talk about how all
of this comes together at a solution
level i'm trying to understand if tbm
does something
wherein you know i deploy a model to a
target architecture but my rest of the
program is in you know x86 it's running
on a server class machine and then you
have these pipelines of data coming in
you know maybe i'm getting click stream
data from the users i'm getting
something from a database and you have
your specialized hardware possibly just
waiting for something to arrive at it
for computation so at a solution level
how do you
how do you see companies like actually
optimizing learning performance and
tuning that tvm produces as i said code
as output that you have to package right
so there's many ways you can actually
package the c runtime with a
well-defined api but then that goes a
little bit outside tv and that's one of
the things that we do at october now as
part of our solution is to be able to
essentially wrap up your model into a
variety of packages that make you
convenient to deploy like you have a
python wheel with python binding that
you can actually call with a
well-defined interface dot so library
you know we can support windows
packaging for example we go where the
customers want to go or a docker
container or a grpc function that you
can deploy and call it as a microservice
then there's many ways in which you can
package it but you know at a solution
level what we provide then is this
various packaging methods and ways of
calling it to just a couple lines of
code right so you absolutely write that
for this to be a viable solution and
actually integrate with the rest of
customer application needs to have the
right package in the right api and
that's why we support a variety of those
so
maybe this was something that i should
have asked earlier when we were talking
about the front end and the back end
parts of the compilers but can someone
go in and look at the intermediate
representation of tvm coming from a
model and then actually hand tune that
yes absolutely yeah and in fact you can
actually print out the tvmir and you can
eyeball it and you can you can go and
actually make transformations you can
write code directly to tdmir if you want
to and in fact some
some specialized operators like one
example that we've done not super
recently but i think in the past year or
so was those sparse operator for
language models that was written
directly in the tvmir and it has a bunch
of benefits because you know you can
express things in a more efficient way
we love to see scenarios like that yeah
yeah i guess it's kind of like not
writing machine code but writing
something at a slightly higher level but
still that's right yeah yeah that's
exactly right so it's sort of like a
slightly higher level but low level
enough for you to express efficient code
right so yeah and i guess you could also
use the ir to understand what the tvm's
interpretation of your model is exactly
to make sure like and you also you have
more more understanding what is it that
did to your model right so at the ir
level too which helps you understand
where the performance coming from it
gives you a choice of what it's doing
and so on yeah it's very interesting so
where do you see this huge
transformation in the machine learning
space going on and two where do you see
tvm going in the future first of all i
think it's undeniable that machine
learning models and ensembles of models
are becoming part of almost every single
interesting application that we interact
with right so from
you know language models applied in
every text that you type to computer
vision being done and in video chats to
you know intelligent user interfaces to
code synthesis and into like just
machine learning models just going
everywhere and
bringing machine learning to the state
of where development regular software
development is today with the right
integration methodologies ci cd
optimization testing compilation all of
this is something that needs to happen i
see this maturity starting to happen
like you know i think as an industry
still relatively early there's a mallops
flow but i firmly believe that as
machine learning ai machine learning
general continues to deliver value and
new experiences and applications are
going to be integral parts and then
there'll be more maturity there and
there'll be more and more
users that would just start integrating
business if you were any other module
right so that's where i see it going
it's becoming just a natural part in how
you build new new applications where sct
them going in the future is more and
more automation and more and more
support for these plethora of
specialized hardware right if you think
about it you know even though we keep
hearing about the ai chips
you know there are very few they're
truly mainstream yet you know nvidia
gpus arguably has a lot of specialized
stuff there and then amd gpus starting
starting to become more and more
interesting for machine learning like in
part because tvm is starting to support
it pretty well but you haven't seen any
other we haven't seen graphcore cerebrus
you know all of these other ones that
are about to hit the market right so and
many others that i'm grok and many
others are about hitting those so we
definitely want to see tvm being you
know again continue to be the
abstraction that you use to not have to
worry about how you get your models
deployed and for that
we need to continue improving to make it
easier to onboard new hardware targets
we have to continue building more
automation to accommodate the front-end
extensions and so on and ict vm
continues to be established as sort of
like this open de facto standard that
support all model frameworks and all
harder targets that people care about so
that's actually very interesting in you
know the systems community in general to
see the sort of rapid
change that's happening through machine
learning based motivated examples right
luis thank you so much for coming on the
show thank you very much it was really
fantastic chad thanks again i really
enjoyed this you're very talented
thanks for uh thanks for coming on this
is akshay manchali for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening